Golden State Mutual Life Insurance Company records LSC.1434
UCLA Library Special Collections
Golden State Mutual Life Insurance Company records
1909-2009
UCLA Library Special Collections
Golden State Mutual Life Insurance Co.
LSC.1434
175 linear feet (156 document boxes, 52 oversize flat boxes, 51 flat boxes, 18 record storage cartons, 11 half document boxes, 9 shoe boxes, 6 tubes, 3 scrapbook/ledger boxes and 1 map folder.)
The Golden State Mutual Life Insurance Company was founded on July 23, 1925 in Los Angeles by William Nickerson Jr., George A. Beavers, Jr., and Norman O. Houston. Their mission was to provide dignified employment for African Americans and to provide them with insurance protection. Golden State Mutual operated for eighty-four years and grew to become one of the largest Black-owned companies in the United States. The collection spans from 1909 to 2009 and consists of minutes books, annual reports, corporate history files, ledgers, public relations and advertising files, correspondence, photographs, scrapbooks, plans, reports, agreements, manuals, policy specimens, Certificates of Contribution and Advancement, publications, files about the company's historical murals and Afro-American art collection, architectural drawings, awards, memorabilia, and audiovisual materials.
Conditions Governing Access
Stored off-site. All requests to access special collections material must be made in advance using the request button located on this page.
Provenance/Source of Acquisition
Gift of Ivan J. Houston, 1986. Additional material was received from the Insurance Commissioner of California, 2014.
UCLA Catalog Record ID
UCLA Catalog Record ID: 9914705923606533
Biography/History
Golden State Mutual founder William Nickerson, Jr. moved to Los Angeles from Texas in 1921 as an official representative of the Texas-based insurance company American Mutual Benefit Association. When he arrived in California, he soon discovered that the state's existing insurance agencies viewed its 40,000 Black citizens as either uninsurables or extraordinary risks. Black residents were only accepted at discriminatory premium rates, or denied insurance coverage altogether.
Nickerson struggled for three years, succeeded in insuring more than 2,000 Californians, only to find that the Texas firm would not renew its California license. To fulfill the promise of protection made to the 2,000 policyowners, Nickerson had to set up a new company. He joined forces with Norman O. Houston, a young insurance salesman from Northern California and George A. Beavers, Jr., a Georgia-born Los Angeles businessman and church leader. Together, in 1924, the three began to shape their dream of creating a Black-owned and operated insurance company.
The state's insurance code required a thorough knowledge of California law governing corporations in general and insurance companies in particular. Nickerson purchased a set of law books, began to study California insurance law and discovered a soon-to-expire law under which the company could be organized as an assessment company. This required that the organizers secure at least 500 applications for life insurance, with premiums paid in advance and that they deposit $15,000 with the state treasurer as a guarantee fund.
Nickerson managed the project, Houston raised the $15,000 through the sale of Certificates of Advancement, and Beavers secured 500 paid applications. Twelve hours before the expiration of the old assessment law, Nickerson, Houston and Beavers received a telegram from the California Department of Insurance informing them that a license to operate had been granted to the Golden State Mutual Guarantee Fund Insurance Company of Los Angeles.
The Company operated out of a 12 by 14 foot second story office at 1435 Central Avenue leased by Board Member and Medical Director Dr. H. H. Towles. The Company was comprised of President William Nickerson, Jr., Secretary and Treasurer Norman O. Houston, Vice-President and Director of Agencies George A. Beavers, Jr., Clerk Helen E. Batiste, and a few agents such as Edgar J. Johnson. After 79 days, the Company moved to a storefront office at 3512 Central Avenue. By the end of 1925, GSM had paid its first death claim and transferred Johnson up north to open and manage its first District Office in Oakland.
Groundbreaking ceremonies for the Company's first Home Office Building were held on August 7, 1928. This 2-story building was located at 4111 Central Avenue. Between 1926 and 1929, GSM established District Offices in Pasadena, Bakersfield, San Diego, Fresno, El Centro and Sacramento.
Changing its name from the Golden State Guarantee Fund Insurance Company to Golden State Mutual Life Insurance Company in 1931, the firm continued to expand. In July of 1938, GSM extended its services to Illinois for the Company's first venture across California boundaries.
During the 1940s, expansion in California saw District Offices established in San Francisco, San Bernardino, Vallejo and Fresno. On January 2, 1942, GSM converted from an assessment company to the more stable status of an old line legal reserve insurer. Out of state expansion carried GSM services to Nickerson's home state of Texas – to Dallas in 1944 and to Houston a year later. The May 27, 1945 opening of the Houston office was the realization of Nickerson's 20-year ambition. Less than six months afterwards, founder William Nickerson, Jr. died on November 14, 1945.
Nickerson's passing brought organizational change to GSM. Norman O. Houston was elected President after serving 20 years as Corporate Secretary and Treasurer. George A. Beavers, Jr. was elected Chairman of the Board and Edgar J. Johnson, became Corporate Secretary.
GSM's continued expansion required that it build a final Home Office in 1948. Designed by architect Paul Revere Williams, this five story structure was completed in the heart of Los Angeles at the intersection of Western Avenue and Adams Boulevard in 1949. The Company's Historical Murals, depicting the history of the Negro in California by Charles Alston and Hale Woodruff were unveiled during the opening week ceremonies for this new building on August 19, 1949.
During the 1950s GSM entered three new states: Oregon, Washington and Arizona. In 1954, the Board of Directors formally declared the Golden Rule as the Company's business philosophy. As a symbolic reminder of this principle, the Company began the practice of presenting to each new employee a marble inscribed with the phrase: Do unto others as you would have them do unto you. In 1957 the Company adopted a new graphic and coined a new nickname for its field representatives. The Golden State agent was reimagined as the Man With The Golden Pen, a name which emphasized the importance of the field underwriter's services to families.
Expansion of services to Michigan and Indiana in 1960 led the Company to enlist a veteran insurance agent from Detroit named Ernest Shell as Assistant Agency Officer. Shell was later to become Senior Vice President, Agency Director and a member of the Company's Board of Directors. During the same year as the Watts riots, GSM celebrated its 40th anniversary and dedicated the Golden State Mutual Afro-American Art Collection. In 1967, George A. Beavers, Jr. resigned as Chairman of the Board. Houston, President since 1945, was elected Chairman and Chief Executive Officer. Edgar J. Johnson, who had served as Executive Vice-President since 1956, was named President and Chief Administrative Officer.
The onset of the 1970s was marked by major management changes. Norman O. Houston retired from active management but remained in the service of the Company as Chairman of the Board of Directors. Edgar J. Johnson also retired but remained as management consultant, member of the Board of Directors and Executive Committee. Ivan J. Houston was elected President and Chief Executive Officer in 1970 and in 1977 when his father vacated his Board Chairmanship, Ivan J. Houston was elected to fill this role in addition to his other duties. By the end of this decade, the Company was licensed to do business in 22 states and the District of Columbia.
Between 1980 and the end of 1984, insurance in force with GSM increased to $4,527,611,000, maintaining its rank as the second largest Black life insurer in the United States by this measure. Organizationally, the Company implemented a modified leadership plan in 1980, electing Larkin Teasley as President and Chief Operating Officer of GSM, with Ivan J. Houston assuming the title of Chairman and Chief Executive Officer.
The following decade saw the retirement of Ivan J. Houston as CEO on December 31, 1990 and Larkin Teasley's election as CEO on January 1, 1991. The new millennium brought forth a 75th year anniversary celebration, a time capsule sealed for over 50 years was opened and a new one encapsulated. Ivan J. Houston retired as Chairman of the Board on March 5, 2001 and Larkin Teasley was elected the new Chairman on the same date. Golden State Mutual closed its doors in 2009 after 84 years of operation.
Scope and Content
The Golden State Mutual Life Insurance Company records range in date from 1909-2009. The collection consists of minutes books, annual reports, corporate history files, ledgers, public relations and advertising files, correspondence, photographs, scrapbooks, plans, reports, agreements, manuals, policy specimens, Certificates of Contribution and Advancement, publications, historical murals and Afro-American art collection files, architectural drawings, awards, memorabilia, and audiovisual materials.
Organization and Arrangement
The collection is arranged in the following series:
Series 1: Corporate History
Series 2: Minutes
Series 3: Annual Statements
Series 4: Financial Records
Series 5: Correspondence
Series 6: Plans, Reports, Agreements and Manuals
Series 7: Policy Specimens and Certificates of Contribution and Advancement
Series 8: Advertising and Publicity Files
Series 9: Historical Murals and Afro-American Art Collection Files
Series 10: Publications
Series 11: Architectural Drawings
Series 12: Awards and Memorabilia
Related Oral Histories
The following oral histories are available through the UCLA Library Center for Oral History Research:
Interview of George A. Beavers [oral history transcript] / George A. Beavers, interviewee. UCLA Oral History Department interview, 1985. UCLA Library Special Collections, Charles E. Young Research Library, University of California, Los Angeles.
Interview of Ivan J. Houston [oral history transcript] / Ivan J. Houston, interviewee. UCLA Oral History Department interview, 1989. UCLA Library Special Collections, Charles E. Young Research Library, University of California, Los Angeles.
Interview of Miriam Matthews [oral history transcript] / Miriam Matthews, interviewee. UCLA Oral History Department interview, 2004. UCLA Library Special Collections, Charles E. Young Research Library, University of California, Los Angeles.
Interview of William Pajaud [oral history transcript] / William Pajaud, interviewee. UCLA Oral History Department interview, 1993. UCLA Library Special Collections, Charles E. Young Research Library, University of California, Los Angeles.
Related Material
Ivan J. Houston papers (Collection 1866). UCLA Library Special Collections, Charles E. Young Research Library, University of California, Los Angeles.
Miriam Matthews papers (Collection 1804). UCLA Library Special Collections, Charles E. Young Research Library, University of California, Los Angeles.
Miriam Matthews Photograph collection (Collection 1889). UCLA Library Special Collections, Charles E. Young Research Library, University of California, Los Angeles.
Online Items Available
Portions of this collection have been digitized and are available online: Golden State Mutual Life Insurance Company records (2823 items)
black-and-white photographs; Account books.; African Americans -- Civil rights -- California -- Los Angeles.; African Americans -- California -- Los Angeles -- History.; Insurance companies -- California -- Los Angeles -- Archives.; African American business enterprises -- California -- Los Angeles -- Archives.; Golden State Mutual Life Insurance Co.--Archives.
- Corporate History, 1911, 1922-2007
  Scope and Content
  The Corporate History series includes files for the following: founder William Nickerson, Jr., co-founders George A. Beavers, Jr. and Norman O. Houston, President and Chief Executive Officer Ivan J. Houston, Public Relations Administrator Verna A. Hickman, historian Titus Alexander and journalist Almena Lomax. Records of corporate history also include photographs, scrapbooks and audiovisual materials.
  - William Nickerson, Jr. files, 1924-1925, 1928, 1930-1961, undated
    Materials include correspondence, architectural specifications, reports, speeches, biographies, memoirs, oral histories, a list of Golden State's first policyholders, clippings and obituaries.
    Biography/History
    Insurance company founder and executive, college graduate, school teacher and political leader, William Nickerson, Jr. was born on January 26, 1879 to a Texas farm couple. Nickerson and his associates organized the American Mutual Benefit Association, the first Negro insurance company in Texas in 1908. Nickerson served as its general secretary for 16 years. During this period, he assisted in bringing the first suit filed in the South to permit Negroes to vote in primary elections. He moved to California in 1921 to supervise expansion of American Mutual but soon after, the firm discontinued its California operations. In Los Angeles, Nickerson joined forces with George A. Beavers, Jr. and Norman O. Houston to found the Golden State Guarantee Fund Insurance Company on July 23, 1925. Nickerson served as Golden State's President until his death on November 14, 1945.
    - Golden State Guarantee Fund Insurance Company correspondence, 1924-1925 (Box 1, Folder 1)
      Nickerson's correspondence with insurance commissioners, judges and lawyers concerning the founding of Golden State Guarantee Fund Insurance Company.
    - 4111 Central Avenue Home Office Dedication Invitation, 1928 December 1 (Box 1, Folder 2)
      Scope and Contents
      Invitation for the Golden State Guarantee Fund Insurance Company's first official Home Office Dedication. Seventy-nine days after Golden State's July 23, 1925 inception in a one room 12-by-14-foot second floor office space located at 1435 Central Avenue, it moved to a 1,400 square foot store front on 3512 Central Avenue for three years. The invitation includes company history, a list of officers and directors, services and its record of progress.
    - Specifications, circa 1928 (Box 1, Folder 3)
      Architectural specifications for the first home office building. These plans by architect James H. Garrott are signed by President Nickerson and Secretary-Treasurer Norman O. Houston.
    - First policyholders list, undated (Box 1, Folder 4)
      Photocopied list of the first 30 policyholders.
    - Letters, reports and addresses, 1930-1945 (Box 1, Folder 5)
      Originals signed by Nickerson and photocopies of his addresses to policyowners, letters to GSM agents and company reports.
    - Earthquake Hazard and Earthquake Protection, 1933 June 6 (Box 1, Folder 6)
      Joint Technical Committee Report on Earthquake Protection includes cover annotation by Nickerson concerning earthquake insurance.
    - Correspondence with Walter A. Gordon, 1938 (Box 1, Folder 7)
      Correspondence between Nickerson and Attorney Walter A. Gordon regarding GSM's Articles of Incorporation and By-Laws.
    - Biographical sketches and addresses, 1938-1949 (Box 1, Folder 8)
      Biographies of Nickerson and memorial addresses. Materials also include honorary birthday memorial booklets and a black and white photo of Nickerson working at his office desk.
    - "Builders of an Empire" clipping, 1939 September 16 (Box 1, Folder 9)
      Pittsburgh Courier newspaper clipping which compares Nickerson's life story to Abraham Lincoln's.
    - Anecdotes and speeches, 1939-1950 (Box 1, Folder 10)
      Originals and photocopies of Nickerson's speeches, speech excerpts, anecdotes, pet phrases and poems.
    - Biographies, 1940-1950 (Box 1, Folder 11)
      Biographies and personal histories include Nickerson's annotations concerning edits. Materials also include Nickerson's "My....Views On Advertisement" and "A Tribute to William Nickerson, Jr." by his daughter Jessie Mae Curry.
    - Memoirs of William Nickerson, Jr., circa 1945 (Box 1, Folder 12)
      Materials include annotated original drafts and photocopies.
    - A Brief Story of the Foundation, History and Objectives of the Now "Golden State Mutual Life Insurance Company", undated (Box 1, Folder 13)
      Typescript by William Nickerson, Jr.
    - Life Story of William Nickerson, Jr., undated (Box 1, Folder 14)
    - Brief History of William Nickerson, Jr., 1947 (Box 1, Folder 15)
      Materials include typescript, personal writings and black and white photographs of Nickerson.
    - Flexograph recordings, 1950 (Box 1, Folder 16)
      Six Gray Flexograph oral history recordings of William Nickerson, Jr.'s wife, Mrs. Bertha Nickerson, their daughter Quincella Nickerson Kimbrough and Luther Hudson of Oakland, California, the first African American mortician in the Bay Area.
    - California Spotlight newspaper, 1951 May 24 (Box 1, Folder 17)
      The front page features "Golden State Mutual, Others Sued for $750,000" by Lawrence F. LaMar of the Negro Press Bureau.
    - Correspondence and Nickerson memorials, 1948-1961 (Box 2, Folder 1)
      Materials include correspondence of gratitude from Bertha Nickerson to Richmond Barthe concerning the William Nickerson, Jr. bust he created, Nickerson memorial addresses and Memorial Planning Committee documents, list of memorial contributors, two color posters of President and Founder Nickerson which include quotes and images of Barthe's bronze bust and brief Nickerson biographies. Materials also include correspondence from GSM Public Relations and Advertising Manager William Pajaud to GSM Chairman of the Board George A. Beavers, Jr. concerning the Nickerson Gardens public housing development designed by Los Angeles architect Paul R. Williams.
    - Obituaries and obsequies, 1945 (Box 2, Folder 2)
      Obituaries and obsequies for William Nickerson, Jr. Materials include biographies, programs, thank you cards and a copy of Nickerson's favorite hymn, "He Knows Just How Much You Can Bear" which was sung at his funeral by Mrs. Marguerite Chapman.
    - News clippings (Box 2, Folder 3)
      Local and national newspaper clippings concerning Nickerson's work as Founder and President of GSM.
  - George A. Beavers, Jr. files, 1925, 1930-1966, 1968, 1970, 1979, 1985, 1989
    Materials include biographical reports, memos, correspondence, memorial resolutions, speeches, clippings, a scrapbook, a programme, an interview transcript, a sermon and a bound copy of his UCLA oral history transcript.
    George A. Beavers, Jr. was born in Atlanta, Georgia on October 30, 1891. When he was twelve, he moved with his family to Los Angeles where he received an education at Los Angeles High School and the University of California, Los Angeles. He became an active member of the First A.M.E. Church on Eighth and Towne and started work with William Nickerson, Jr. in 1922 as an agent for the American Mutual Benefit Association. Beavers joined Norman O. Houston in 1924 to assist Nickerson with the foundation of the Golden State Guarantee Fund Insurance Company. When the doors of its one room office opened in 1925, Beavers' sister, Helen Hodge Batiste became the Company's first clerk and later, first female senior officer and member of its Board of Directors. George Beavers, Jr. served Golden State as its Vice President and Director of Agencies from 1925-1945 and then served as its Chairman of the Board until his retirement on October 25, 1966. As a civil servant, Beavers served as Commissioner of the Los Angeles Housing Authority from 1946 to 1962 and as a civil rights advocate, Beavers was a lifetime member of the NAACP, President and Director of the Los Angeles Urban League and Chairman of the State Commission on Equal Opportunities in Education. Additionally, in 1942, as President of Allied Organizations Against Discrimination in National Defense, Beavers led a campaign that opened the doors of war industries to Negro workers on the Pacific Coast. Beavers died in Los Angeles on October 12, 1989.
    - Charter Membership Contest, 1925 (Box 2, Folder 4)
      This document records Beavers as the winner.
    - Sermon, 1925 May 17 (Box 2, Folder 5)
      Copy of a sermon delivered by the late Reverend N.P. Greggs, who founded the People's Independent Church of Christ in Los Angeles in 1915. This was the first sermon ever preached in the interest of Golden State Mutual Life Insurance Company.
    - Biographical reports and memos, 1930-1964 (Box 2, Folder 6)
      Multiple versions of biographical reports and copies of GSM memos from Beavers as Chairman of the Board.
    - Speeches (Box 2, Folder 7-10)
      Handwritten and typed speeches. Materials also include notes on index cards and various slips of paper.
    - "Can You Dig It?", 1970 (Box 2, Folder 11)
      Letter to co-workers from Beavers serving as retired GSM Chairman of the Board and Co-Founder. The letter's subheading reads, "Diamonds in Your Own Black Yard" and charts company history with a focus on the first Home Office groundbreaking at 4261 South Central Avenue.
    - News clippings, 1944-1955 (Box 2, Folder 12)
      Newspaper and magazine clippings regarding Beavers' work for GSM.
    - Handbook for Stenographers and Cashiers, 1947 August (Box 2, Folder 13)
      This handbook belonged to Mabel Cleveland, who began work with GSM in 1941. Cleveland aided in the conversion of the company to an Old Line Legal Reserve insurer. She performed secretarial services for William Nickerson, Jr., George A. Beavers, Jr. and Norman O. Houston. Eventually she became Secretary to the President.
    - Ranking of Companies by Insurance in Force, 1948 (Box 2, Folder 14)
      Copy of The National Underwriter ranking that documents total insurance in force for 1944-1947 and amount of increase from 1946-1947.
    - Souvenir Programme and History of People's Independent Church of Christ, 1935 October 6 (Box 3, Folder 1)
      Materials include black and white photos and Beavers' history of the church.
    - Pittsburgh Courier clipping, 1948 May 15 (Box 3, Folder 2)
      Copy of a GSM newspaper clipping from the paper's "Business Review" section and a related memo from Beavers to all company personnel.
    - Memos, 1949-1965 (Box 3, Folder 3)
      GSM memos from Chairman of the Board Beavers. Memos focus on company accomplishments and include inspirational quotations, anecdotes and poetry.
    - News clippings, 1951, 1958, 1968 (Box 3, Folder 4)
      Los Angeles Times and Los Angeles Review clippings concerning desegregation, housing bias, and Beavers' election to President of the Los Angeles Urban League Board of Directors.
    - Correspondence, 1961-1963 (Box 3, Folder 5)
      Letters to Beavers during his service as GSM's Chariman of the Board. Materials include black and white photos of Board members.
    - Insurance Association 43rd Annual Convention scrapbook, 1963 August 19-22 (Box 3, Folder 6)
      Beavers' scrapbook of conference clippings and black and white photos includes a photo of him on a panel with the Rev. Dr. Martin Luther King, Jr.
    - Retirement program file, 1966 October 28 (Box 3, Folder 7)
      File includes Beavers' retirement program and related correspondence, memos, speeches and clippings.
    - Los Angeles City Council Resolution, 1968 June 11 (Box 3, Folder 8)